Finding Aid for Raymond W. Waggoner Papers 1926-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Papers and Addresses
  - 1961
    - Report of Behavioral Science Visit to Russia (Box 9)
  - 1962
    - Newsletter of Michigan Society of Psychiatry and Neurology (Box 9)
    - Psychiatric Units in general Hospitals (Box 9)
    - Media Addresses (Box 9)
  - 1964
    - Communications with a Patient (Box 9)
    - ... Disturbed Child with Petit Mal Epilepsy (Box 9)
    - The Treatment of Drug Addiction (Box 9)
  - 1965
    - Some Thoughts About Residency Training (Box 9)
    - Narcotic Addiction (Box 9)
    - Emotional Factors in Headache (Box 9)
    - Liver Disease and Brain Pathology (Box 9)
  - 1966
    - Psychiatric Training Programs in Medical Centers (Box 9)
    - Visually Evoked Responses in Migraine (Box 9)
    - Discussion (Box 9)
    - The Future of Psychologically Oriented Psychiatry... (Box 9)
    - Discussion of Papers by Ruesch and Millet (Box 9)
    - Marriage Counseling as a Responsibility of the Physician (Box 9)
    - Physiological Complaints in Depression (Box 9)
    - Psychiatric Training Programs (Box 9)
    - Reparative and Reconstructive Processes in Psychoanalysis and Psychotherapy (Box 9)
    - Some Comments on Training (Box 9)
    - Why So Many Psychiatrists (Box 9)
    - Post-Graduate Psychiatric Education (Box 9)
  - 1967
    - Unilateral and Bilateral Electroconvulsive Therapy (Box 9)
    - Selection and Induction (Box 9)
    - Physiological Complaints in Depression (Box 9)
  - 1968
    - Effects of Psychiatric Interview ... on Emotionally Disturbed Children (Box 9)
    - Forced Publication: the Abuse of Talent (Box 9)
    - Forensic Perspectives for Aggression and Violence (Box 9)
    - Violence and Aggression (Box 9)
    - Conference on Mental Health in the Americas (Box 9)
    - Population Crisis and the Psychiatrist (Box 9)
    - Somatic Concomitants of Depression (Box 9)
  - 1969
    - Carrier Clinic (Box 9)
    - Current Changes in the APA (Box 9)
    - Dedicatory Address, Penn Foundation for Mental Health (Box 9)
    - Depression (Box 9)
    - Specialty Salesman Magazine (Box 9)
    - Facing the Challenge of Today (Box 9)
    - Our Responsibility as Psychiatrists (Box 9)
    - What Questions on Sex are Most Frequently Asked By Your Patients (Box 9)
    - Response to the Presidential Address (Box 9)
    - Psychiatry in the Modern World (Box 9)
    - Remarks, Canadian Psychiatric Association (Box 9)
    - The Social Responsibility of the Psychiatrist (Box 9)
    - Welcome Perplexity (Box 9)
  - 1970
    - Cultural Dissonance and Psychiatry (Box 9)
    - Emotional factors of Headache (Box 9)
    - The Future of International Psychiatry (Box 9)
    - The Future of Cross-Cultural Psychiatry (Box 9)
    - Marriage Counseling (Box 9)
    - Masters and Johnson Techniques (Box 9)
    - Patient-Therapist Communication (Box 9)
    - Psychiatric Responsibilities (Box 9)
    - Recollections of the President, Eastern Psychoanalytic Association (Box 9)
    - The Relationship of Drugs to Social Dissonance (Box 9)
    - Restructuring the APA for the, 1970s (Box 9)
    - Social Dissonance (Box 9)
    - Somatic Concomitants of Depression (Box 9)
  - 1971
    - Sexual Education and Psychiatry (Box 9)
  - 1972
    - Training of Dual Sex Teams (Box 9)
  - 1973
    - Sexual Function and Dysfunction in Middle Life (Box 9)
  - Papers and Addresses, Undated
    - Chairman's Comments at Workshop on Graduate Psychiatric Education (Box 10)
    - Changing Concepts of Psychiatric Residency Training (Box 10)
    - Clinical Aspects of Tranquilizing Drugs (Box 10)
    - Comments Concerning Mental Health of Important Figures in History (Box 10)
    - Comments Made at Dedication of the Jefferson Medical College Unit (Box 10)
    - Comments on "Applications of General Systems Theory in Industry and Community" (Box 10)
    - Comments on Psychiatric Responsibility (Box 10)
    - Current Changes in the APA (Box 10)
    - Drugs and Behavior (Box 10)
    - The Early Recognition of Behavioral Disturbances (Box 10)
    - Epilepsy in Temporal Lobe Tumors, circa 1952-1953 (Box 10)
    - Headache (Box 10)
    - Histopathology of the Brain in an Electrocoma Death (Box 10)
    - Import of the Adolescent to Psychiatry (Box 10)
    - The Integration of Therapy (Box 10)
    - Interests in Psychiatry (Box 10)
    - Liver Disease and Brain Pathology (Box 10)
    - Masters and Johnson (Box 10)
    - Mental Health: Suggestions for the Future (Box 10)
    - Michigan Society of Pastoral Care (Box 10)
    - The Philosophy of Psychiatric Residency Training (Box 10)
    - Population Crisis and the Psychiatrist (Box 10)
    - Psychiatric Considerations of Peace Corps Volunteer Selection and Indoctrination (Box 10)
    - Psychiatric Education (Box 10)
    - Psychiatric Factors in Medical Students in Difficulty, circa 1948 (Box 16)
      [CR until January 1, 2023 ]
    - Psychiatric Induction Station Procedures During World War II (Box 10)
    - Psychiatric Problems of the War (UM Broadcasting Service) (Box 10)
    - Psychiatric Units in General Hospitals, circa 1960 (Box 10)
    - Residency Training in Psychiatry (Box 10)
    - Social Dissonance: Alfred Noyes Memorial Lecture (Box 10)
    - Social Turmoil (Box 10)
    - Some Unusual Psychophysiologic Problems (Box 10)
    - A Study in Communication (Box 10)
    - A Study of Affects in the Emotionally Disturbed Child with a Convulsive Disorder (Box 10)
    - Symposium on the Newer Chemotherapeutic Aids in Nervous and Mental Disorders (Box 10)
    - Three Areas of Basic Needs in the Mental Health Field in Michigan (Box 10)
    - Training in Mental Health (Box 10)
    - The Treatment of Drug Addiction (Box 10)
    - Trends and Issues in Psychiatric Residency Programs (Box 10)
    - The Use of Psychotropic Drugs in General Practice (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Topics, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Correspondence
  The arrangement of the Correspondence series (5 linear ft.; 1937-1976) reflects Waggoner's filing system. Material has been arranged in three subseries: chronologically, alphabetically by organization name, and alphabetically by name of correspondent. The Chronological files are mainly collegial, work-related yet informal letters. The Organization files overlap somewhat with the contents of the Topical Files, although they are more likely to contain plans for conferences and symposia, and are generally less formal and "official" than the Topical Files; this subseries contains more extensive correspondence regarding the APA.
  The final subseries, correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent, contains correspondence with medical and academic colleagues, friends, politicians, and a few patients. Letters from or about patients have been pulled out of sequence and filed chronologically within "Patient Information Files," to be open for research 100 years from when they were written.
  - Chronological, 1937-1969; 9 folders (Box 10)
  - Alphabetical by Organization
    - American Academy of Psychoanalysis (AAP)
      - General, 1968-1971 (Box 11)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Brochure, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
      - Committee on Liaison with Other Scientific Organizations, 1956-1957 (Box 11)
      - Committee on Psychoanalytic Education, 1964-1969 (Box 11)
      - Historical Committee, 1968 (Box 11)
      - Workshop on Psychoanalytic Training, 1964-1965 (Box 11)
    - American Bar Foundation
      - General, 1968-1970 (Box 11)
      - Advisory Board of Psychiatrists, 1962-1965 (Box 11)
      - Mental Illness and the Law, 1960-1966 (Box 11)
    - American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, Inc.
      - Child Psychiatry Training Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 11)
      - Report on Residency Training in Psychiatry, 1952 (Box 11)
    - American College of Psychiatrists
      - General, 1963-1976; 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Annual Meeting, 1974 (Box 11)
      - Constitution, Committees, Members, 1965-1970 (Box 11)
      - Membership Letters, 1966-1970 (Box 11)
      - Minutes and Reports, 1966 (Box 11)
      - New Orleans Seminars, 1968-1969; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Residents, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
    - American Group Psychotherapy Association, 1968 (Box 11)
    - American Medical Association (AMA)
      - General, 1961-1971 (Box 11)
      - Council on Mental Health, 1974 (Box 11)
    - American Psychiatric Association (APA)
      - Academy for Educational Development (interviews), undated (Box 11)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Black Psychiatrists, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Conflicts in Psychiatry, 1972-1973; 3 folders (Box 11)
      - American Journal of Psychiatry, 1966-1971 (Box 11)
      - Annual Meetings, 1967-1971; 5 folders (Box 11)
      - Applications and Lists of Residences, 1957-1962 (Box 11)
      - Automobile Accident Panel, 1967 (Box 11)
      - Barton, Walter, Medical Director, 1969-1971 (Box 11)
      - Caribbean Psychiatric Association, 1969 (Box 11)
      - Commission on the Delivery of Mental Health Services, 1969-1971; 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Committee Meeting, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Committee on Constitution and By-laws, 1969-1970 (Box 12)
      - Committee on Conventions, 1969 (Box 12)
      - Committee on National Defense, 1957-1961 (Box 12)
      - Ethics Committee, 1969-1975
        - General, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Dr. N. Shainess, 1970-1972 (Box 12)
      - Fourth Divisional Meeting, New York, 1967 (Box 12)
      - Garber, Robert, 1970-1971 (Box 12)
      - General, 1967-1974; 9 folders (Box 12)
      - Hawaii Meeting, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Hogan, Bart, Deputy Medical Director, 1968-1971 (Box 12)
      - Mexico City Meeting, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Nominating Committee, 1969-1975; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Round the World Trip, 1963 (Box 12)
      - San Diego District Branch, 1969-1970 (Box 12)
      - Seattle Meeting, 1969 (Box 12)
      - Southern California Psychiatric Society, 1972-1973 (Box 12)
      - Symposium: "Closing the Gap Between Medicine and Psychiatry,", 1969 (Box 12)
      - Task Force on Psychiatry and Foreign Affairs, 1969 (Box 12)
      - Task Force to Plan a Joint Meeting in Europe, 1971 (Box 12)
      - Technical Assistance Committee, White House Conference on Children, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Washington Psychiatric Society, 1969-1970 (Box 12)
      - "Winds of Change" Conference Reports, 1971 (Box 12)
    - American Psychopathological Association Meeting, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Association of Medical Superintendents of Mental Hospitals, 1966-1970 (Box 13)
    - The Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists, 1970-1972 (Box 13)
    - Canadian Psychiatric Association, 1969 (Box 13)
    - Central Neuropsychiatric Association, 1965-1974; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Dallas Southern Clinical Society, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Department of Defense Industrial Personnel Security, 1969 (Box 13)
    - Department of Health, Education and Welfare
      - General, 1962-1970 (Box 13)
      - National Institute of Mental Health, 1965-1971 (Box 13)
      - Reorganization, 1968-1970 (Box 13)
    - Eastern Psychoanalytic Association, 1970-1974 (Box 13)
    - Food and Drug Administration, 1968 (Box 13)
    - Group for the Advancement of Psychiatry, 1966-1971 (Box 13)
    - Group for Progressive Psychiatry, 1974 (Box 13)
    - Illinois Psychiatric Society, 1968 (Box 13)
    - Inter-American Conference on Mental Health, 1968-1969 (Box 13)
    - International Seminar on Youth, 1968 (Box 13)
    - Joint Commission on Manpower and Training, 1965 (Box 13)
    - Joint Committee for Stroke Facilities, 1970-1974 (Box 13)
    - Medical Advisory Board on Educational Film Production, 1966-1969 (Box 13)
    - Michigan Department of Mental Health-Director Selection Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 13)
    - Midwest Professors of Psychiatry, 1964-1968 (Box 13)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1962-1972 (Box 13)
    - National Association for Mental Health, Inc., 1952-1962 (Box 13)
    - National Association for Private Psychiatric Hospitals, 1968-1969 (Box 13)
    - National Board of Medical Examiners, 1968-1970; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - National Committee Against Mental Illness, 1952 (Box 13)
    - National Institute of Mental Health Conference on Community Psychiatry, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    - National Mental Health Act, 1949 (Box 13)
    - National Paraplegia Foundation, Inc., 1957-1968 (Box 13)
    - National Research Council, Division of Medical Science, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Research Societies Council, 1966-1967 (Box 13)
    - Selective Service System, 1967-1968 (Box 13)
    - Social Security Admin., 1966-1970 (Box 16)
      [CR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2070 ]
    - Society of Biological Psychiatry, 1963-1967 (Box 13)
    - Veterans Administration, 1968-1969 (Box 16)
    - World Congress of Psychiatry, 1965-1966 (Box 13)
    - Waggoner Society, 1968-1970 (Box 13)
  - Alphabetical by Correspondent
    - Miscellaneous Personal, 2 folders
      - 1925-1929 (Box 13)
      - 1938-1974 (Box 16)
    - A, 1958-1975 (Box 13)
    - Anderson, Gottlieb and Enelow, 1967-1969 (Box 13)
    - B, 1963-1975 (Box 13)
    - Balser, Benjamin H., 1954-1967 (Box 13)
    - Barclay, Hartley, 1972 (Box 13)
    - Bartemeier, Leo H., 1960-1970 (Box 13)
    - Barton, Walter, 1962-1973 (Box 13)
    - Beaubrun, Michael H., 1969-1971 (Box 13)
    - Behavioral Science (journal), 1970 (Box 13)
    - Boyd, David A., 1939-1971 (Box 13)
    - Braceland, Francis J., 1944-1972 (Box 13)
    - Brill, Norman Q., 1958-1971 (Box 14)
    - Brosin, Henry W., 1959-1970 (Box 14)
    - Brown, Bertram, 1970-1974 (Box 14)
    - Burr, Charles W., 1926-1927 (Box 14)
    - C, 1958-1976 (Box 14)
    - Camp, Carl D., 1929 (Box 14)
    - Canadian Professors of Psychiatry, 1967 (Box 14)
    - Carmichael, Hugh T., 1962-1969 (Box 14)
    - Dean, Stanley R., 1969-1975 (Box 14)
    - DeJong, Russell N., 1969 (Box 16)
    - Donahue, Hayden H., 1972-1973 (Box 14)
    - Dorsey, John, 1958-1973 (Box 14)
    - Dukay, Alexander, 1971-1972 (Box 16)
      [CR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2072 ]
    - Esch, Marvin, 1968-1975 (Box 14)
    - E-F, 1959-1974 (Box 14)
    - Fischer, Aart A., 1964-1965 (Box 14)
    - Fiske, Seymour, 1960-1961 (Box 14)
    - Ford, Hamilton, 1970-1975 (Box 14)
    - Furstenberg, Dean A.C., 1949-1959 (Box 14)
    - G, 1958-1976 (Box 14)
    - Geigy Symposium, 1973 (Box 14)
    - Gottlieb, Jack S., 1962-1969 (Box 14)
    - Grover, Gregory, 1962-1974 (Box 14)
    - H, 1956-1975 (Box 14)
    - Hall Psychiatric Institute, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
    - Halleck, Seymour, 1970 (Box 14)
    - Harris, Titus H., 1959-1961 (Box 14)
    - Hart, Senator Philip A., 1967-1969 (Box 14)
    - Hatcher, President Harlan, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Haynes, H.A., 1938-1945 (Box 14)
    - Heldt, Thomas J., 1958-1971 (Box 14)
    - Hill, Sir Denis, 1968-1969 (Box 16)
    - Holt Institute, 1972-1973 (Box 14)
    - Hubbard, Dean William, 1959-1962 (Box 14)
    - I-J, 1969-1975; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - K, 1959-1975 (Box 14)
    - Kelly, Governor Harry F., 1946-1950 (Box 14)
    - Kerlikowske, A.C., 1938-1962 (Box 14)
    - L, 1964-1974 (Box 14)
    - Lehrman, Nathaniel S., 1961-1962 (Box 14)
    - Lief, Harold I., 1960-1976 (Box 14)
    - Light, Donald, 1974 (Box 14)
    - Lovell, Harold W., 1967-1968 (Box 14)
    - Loyola University, 1969-1970 (Box 14)
    - M, 1962-1976 (Box 14)
    - McCallum, Senator George P., 1938-1939 (Box 14)
    - Marshall, General S.L.A., 1962-1971 (Box 16)
    - Martin, Peter, 1964-1974 (Box 14)
    - Masserman, Jules, 1961-1976 (Box 14)
    - Menniger, William B., 1942-1950; 1954-1968 (Box 14)
    - Meynet, Maria Christine, 1966-1968 (Box 14)
    - Morse, Robert T., 1960-1975 (Box 14)
    - Mudd, Emily H., 1970-1976 (Box 14)
    - N, 1961-1976 (Box 14)
    - Nixon, Richard M., 1968-1974 (Box 14)
    - Noyes Memorial Conference, 1969 (Box 14)
    - O, 1962-1975 (Box 15)
    - Overholser, Winifred, 1954-1963 (Box 15)
    - P, 1959-1976 (Box 15)
    - Pack, Col. Philip C., 1945-1946 (Box 15)
    - Patient Information, chronological order, 1959-1976; 2 folders (Box 16)
      [CR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2076 ]
    - Patterson, Ralph M., 1959-1965 (Box 15)
    - Peterson, Donald B., 1959-1965 (Box 15)
    - Proctor, Lorne D., 1952-1955 (Box 15)
    - R, 1961-1976 (Box 15)
    - Ramsey, Vestal, 1958-1961 (Box 16)
      [CR RESTRICTED until January 1, 2061 ]
    - Rathana-Nakintara, Thaworn, 1960-1971 (Box 15)
    - Reckless, John, 1972-1976 (Box 15)
    - Rees, John Rawlings, 1958-1959 (Box 15)
    - Ross, Matthew, 1959-1963 (Box 15)
    - Ruthven, Alexander G., 1942-1945 (Box 15)
    - S, 1964-1976 (Box 15)
    - Schmidhofer, Ernst, 1959-1962 (Box 15)
    - Snyder Hearing, 1969 (Box 15)
    - Stunkard, Albert J., 1965-1967 (Box 15)
    - T, 1964-1976 (Box 15)
    - Taylor Manor Hospital, 1970-1973 (Box 15)
    - Tennessee Squire, 1966-1968 (Box 15)
    - Tien, H.C., 1968-1969 (Box 15)
    - Towsley, Harry, 1959-1971 (Box 15)
    - U-W, 1964-1976; 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Waggoner, Raymond W., Jr., 1972-1975 (Box 15)
    - Ward, Patricia, 1974-1975 (Box 15)
    - Williams, Governor G. Mennen, 1949-1955 (Box 15)
    - X-Z, 1964-1974 (Box 15)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (.2 linear ft.; ca.1930s-1972) includes portraits and candid photographs of Waggoner, as well as pictures of Neuropsychiatric Institute staff, residents and interns. There are also pictures of NPI buildings and other University of Michigan psychiatric treatment buildings, most of which were photographed in the 1950s.
  - Children's Psychiatric Hospital, circa 1950s (Box 15)
  - Class of 1924 Reunion (Medical School), circa 1940s, 1924-1949 (Box 15)
  - Colleagues, undated (Box 15)
  - Conferences and Candids, circa 1940s-1972 (Box 15)
  - Detention Screens, circa 1950s (Box 15)
  - Neuropsychiatric Institute Buildings and Scenes, circa 1950s (Box 15)
  - Neuropsychiatric Institute Residents and Interns, 1956-1970 (Box 15)
  - Neuropsychiatric Institute Staff, circa 1950s (Box 15)
  - Portraits of RWW, circa 1930s-1972 (Box 15)
  - UM Psychiatric Treatment Buildings, circa 1950s (Box 15)
- Awards, Honors, Certificates
  Awards, Honors, Certificates includes diplomas, certificates, and examples of honors received by Waggoner throughout his career.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)